The popular narrative is that Palestinians were offered a state time after time and they're just so full of hatred and, you know, being irrational that they kept rejecting time and time again.
This is Fatih Namir, a Palestine policy fellow at Al Shabaka.
He explained what went wrong at the Camp David summit in 2000, which were peace talks between the U.S., Israel and the Palestinian Authority.
He said Camp David acts as a case study for the peace talks throughout the years.
Camp David is kind of presented as the very generous offer that Arafat refused.
It's shown as like this is the big evidence that the Palestinians are not interested in peace.
And it's thrown around by people who don't actually know any of the details of what was being offered on the table and all the counterproposals.
The propagandas that Ehud Barak offered the Palestinians the entirety of the West Bank, but he refused to evacuate any of the settlements.
We're talking about a huge number of settlers.
So that effectively annexed 10 percent of the West Bank.
He then suggested another 10 percent be annexed for quote unquote security reasons.
So that's already 20 percent of the West Bank that was annexed before even beginning the negotiations.
He suggested that a strip of land between Palestine and Jordan would be also annexed for security reasons.
Palestinians would not be in control of their own airspace.
That would be under Israeli control.
They would not be in control of their borders completely.
The water situation would remain unchanged, which means that Israel would continue to control the most of the water in the West Bank, even though it's underneath the West Bank.
The second thing is that they wanted three permanent military installations in the West Bank.
They wanted the right to invade Palestinian territory at any time in the future in a case of an emergency.
Of course, what was considered an emergency was not defined.
It was left vague on purpose so that it could be justified whenever they invaded.
And the cherry on top, of course, is Jerusalem.
According to international law, East Jerusalem was occupied in 1967 and it was supposed to form the capital of the Palestinian state, while West Jerusalem would serve as the capital of the Israeli state.
Israel rejected the majority of the demands regarding that.
They said that sovereignty of East Jerusalem would remain firmly within the hands of the Israeli state.
Even though the Palestinians said that, hey, you could take sovereignty over the Jewish neighborhoods, Jewish holy sites, all of that, take it for Israel.
Even the settlements, the illegal settlements, they were agreeing to maintain the illegal settlements in East Jerusalem under Israeli control in return for a kind of, you know, land swap, which never materialized, obviously.
But this was rejected.
These are the kinds of offers that Palestinians were given.
Like, it is not an actual sovereign state.
There was never an intention to have an actual sovereign state.
And rejecting such a thing is not irrational.
Hlomo Ben-Ami, who was the foreign minister at the time, who was one of the chief negotiators for the Israeli team, he said that...
Camp David was not the missed opportunity for the Palestinians.
And if I were a Palestinian, I would have rejected Camp David as well.
But this all gets buried underneath the propaganda because it was important to create or craft the narrative that the Palestinians are intransigent and they refuse peace.
And that is what was succeeded.